<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Prayers for the Parliament</title>
            <author>Church of England.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1606</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 5 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 3 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A21439</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 7748.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S3306</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">33143297</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 33143297</idno>
            <idno type="VID">28365</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A21439)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 28365)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1885:19)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Prayers for the Parliament</title>
                  <author>Church of England.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>R. Barker,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1606?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>With an added thanksgiving following the 2nd collect, mentioning "our deliuerance from those great and apparant dangers, wherwith we were compassed in this place."</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Society of Antiquaries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Liturgy.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Prayer-books and devotions.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:28365:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 19 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:28365:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 19 -->
            <head>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>garland embellished with Tudor rose</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </head>
            <head>¶ Prayers for the Parliament.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Od be merciful vnto vs and bleſſe vs:<note place="margin">Pſalm. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and ſhewe vs the light of his countenance, and be mercifull vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to vs.</p>
            <p>That thy way may be knowen vpon earth, thy ſauing health a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all Nations.</p>
            <p>Let y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> people praiſe thee, O God: yea, let all the people praiſe thee.</p>
            <p>O let the Nations reioyce and be glad, for thou ſhalt iudge the folke righteouſly: and gouerne the Nations vpon earth.</p>
            <p>Let the people praiſe thee, O God: let all the people praiſe thee.</p>
            <p>Then ſhal the earth bring forth her increaſe: and God, euen our owne God, ſhall giue vs his bleſſing.</p>
            <p>God ſhall bleſſe vs: and all the ends of the world ſhal feare him.</p>
            <div type="intercessory_prayers">
               <head>After the Pſalme, theſe Suffrages.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Lord be with you.</p>
               <p>
                  <label>Anſwere.</label>
                  <lb/>
And with thy ſpirit.</p>
               <p>¶ Let vs pray.
<list>
                     <item>Lord haue mercy vpon vs.</item>
                     <item>
                        <pb facs="tcp:28365:2"/>
                        <!-- PDF PAGE 20 -->
Chriſt haue mercie vpon vs.</item>
                     <item>Lord haue mercie vpon vs.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>¶ Our Father which art in heauen, &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="collects">
               <head>
                  <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> Then ſhall follow three Collects.</head>
               <div n="1" type="part">
                  <head>The firſt for the Kings Maieſtie.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>
                     </hi> Lord our heauenly Father, high and mighty, King of Kings, Lord of Lords, the onely ruler of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which doeſt from thy Throne behold all y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> dwellers vpon earth, moſt heartily we beſeech thee with thy fauor to behold our moſt graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Soueraign Lord King <hi>Iames,</hi> and ſo repleniſh him with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grace of thy holy Spirit, that he may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way encline to thy will, and walke in thy way: endue him plenteouſly with heauenly giftes, graunt him in health and wealth long to liue, ſtrengthen him, that hee may vanquiſh and ouercome all his enemies, and finally after this life he may attaine euerlaſting ioy and felicitie, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. Amen.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>The ſecond Collect.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Lmightie God, which by thy holy Prophet Dauid art moſt truly ſaid to ſtand in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> congregation of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and giueſt iudgement in the middeſt of the mighty men of the world, and through whoſe autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie Princes doe reigne, Law ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers do diſcerne iuſt things, Lords beare rule, and all Iudges of the earth execute iudgement, and for that commeth of thee all counſaile and equitie, all vnderſtanding and ſtrength: Grant vnto vs here gathered together in thy Name, that
<pb facs="tcp:28365:2"/>
                     <!-- PDF PAGE 20 -->Wiſedome which is alwaies aſſiſtant to thy ſeat, to giue knowledge to our feeble and ignorant mindes. Send downe (we beſeech thee) the ſame Wiſedome out of thy holy heauens, and from the throne of thy Maieſtie, that it may be now with vs, and labour with vs, whereby we ſurely knowing what is acceptable vnto thee, may be led through it to the debating, weighing, and finall determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of thoſe matters, by the which thy bleſſed Name may be glorified, thy Catholique Church of England confirmed &amp; increaſed, the Kings aſſurance eſtabliſhed, the common tranquillitie of this Realme ſafely main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, and laſt of all, all eſtates and people therof, in true obedience and charitie vnited and knit together. Grant this, O God, for thy onely Sonnes ſake Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. Amen.</p>
                  <div type="prayer_of_thanksgiving">
                     <head>A Thankeſgiuing for peace and Victory.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>
                           <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>
                        </hi> Almightie God, which art a ſtrong Tower of defence vnto thy ſeruants a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the face of their enemies: wee yeeld thee praiſe and Thankſgiuing for our deliuerance from thoſe great and apparant dangers, wherwith we were compaſſed in this place: Wee acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge it thy goodnes, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we were not deliuered ouer as a prey vnto them: beſeeching thee ſtill to continue ſuch thy mercies towards vs, that all the world may know, that thou art our Sauiour and Mighty deliuerer, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. Amen.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>The third Collect.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Reuent vs, O Lord, in all our doings, with thy moſt Gracious fauour, and further vs with thy continuall helpe, that in all our works begunne, continued, and ended in thee,
<pb facs="tcp:28365:3"/>
                     <!-- PDF PAGE 21 -->we may glorifie thy holy Name, and finally by thy mercy obtaine euerlaſting life through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="benediction">
               <head>Then ſhall follow the Benediction, as thus.</head>
               <p>
                  <bibl>2. CORINTH. 13.</bibl>
                  <q>THe Grace of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, and the loue of God, and the fellowſhip of the holy Ghoſt, be with vs all euermore. Amen.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
